Guide to the Personal Papers of Carroll Newsom 1924-1986 MC.122
New York University Archives
Carroll Newsom Papers
1924-1986
New York University Archives
MC.122
6 Linear Feet in 11 boxes
Carroll Newsom was a businessman and scholar who was President of NYU from 1956-1962. The papers include Newsom's addresses, especially those given while at NYU and during the 1960's in general, publications by Newsom in journals and periodicals from 1940-1973, publications about Newsom relating to his role on advisory committes (e.g., curriculum survey of the New York State University system), programs which document the various functions he attended, miscellaneous materials (correspondence, reviews of Newsom's books, and diplomas), and newspapers and newspaper clippings relating to important events in his career.
Arrangement
The materials have been divided into print and non-print materials, contained in eleven manuscript boxes. Folders are arranged chronologically within each series.
The collection is divided into five series:
Missing Title
Series I:Addresses
Series II:Publications
Series III:Programs
Series IV:Miscellaneous Materials
Series V: Newspapers and Newspaper Clippings.
Physical Access
Please note that this collection is stored offsite, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Separated Material
Photos were removed and place in the University Archives photo collection.
Related Material
Archives H biographical files.
Scope and Content Note
The materials contained in this collection are strong in highlighting the ideas, ideals, and philosophy of Newsom as expressed in his many academic and corporate roles, but offer little original information with regard to his tenure as President of New York University. The collection is divided into five main series, as well as a supplementary photo collection which is located in the greater photo collection(see Cross-Reference sheet for further information regarding the Newsom photos.)
This collection contains no administrative records of Dr. Newsom, either while President of New York University or in any of his subsequent positions. The inclusive dates of the collection are 1924 to 1986.
Historical/Biographical Note:
Carroll Newsom's illustrious career, amply showcased in a resume which lists 52 major positions, 37 "minor positions," 9 published books and 24 honorary degrees (in addition to three earned degrees), is only partially illuminated by the materials contained in this collection. Nonetheless, the Newsom papers offer a glimpse of his career beyond his position as President of New York University, and are of particular value in contributing to a knowledge of the ideas, philosophy, and achievements of this hybrid businessman-scholar.
Carroll Newsom graduated from the College of Emporia, Kansas in 1924, receiving his A.B. degree in mathematics. A prodigy in mathematics, Newsom became an instructor of mathematics at the University of Michigan in 1927, the institution from which he received his M.A. in 1927 and PhD. in 1931. His achievements at this university anticipate his later career. Reworking the traditional mathematics curriculum of the university, which Newsom characterized simply as being "bad," Newsom had become a full professor and department chairman in the astonishingly short space of five years.
During the Second World War, and the consequent increased demand for mathematicians and scientists, Newsom took a position as Chairman of the Science Division at Oberlin College. Newsom had already written about both the positive and negative potential of atomic energy(in An American Philosophy of Education). During one meeting with a nervous President Truman, Newsom advised the new President to continue with the Manhattan Project, after Truman had asked him, "Do you think this is something I should pursue?"
At the war's end, Newsom and two other American doctors helped to reorganize medical education in France, for which Newsom was later awarded the French Legion of Honor. Taking leave of Oberlin in 1948, Newsom moved on to New York, where he took the post of Assistant Commissioner of Higher Education in 1948. As Associate Commissioner from 1950 to 1955, Newsom was instrumental in developing the state university system.
Newsom's last stop on the educational trail was at New York University, first as Executive Vice President from 1955 to 1956, then as President from 1956 to 1962 (his resignation took effect on January 1, 1962 ). His tenure as NYU President was considered by the university trustees to be "the most fruitful in the university's history, in the increase of financial resources and in building expansion." During his presidency, NYU's assets increased from $111 million to $178 million, a total of $70 million in gifts having been received during his tenure as President.
Newsom moved on to the Senior Vice President slot at Prentice-Hall, becoming president and director of the publishing firm in 1964. Yet once again, Newsom's brief tenure at Prentice-Hall resembled that of a corporate raider, as he left the presidency of the firm in 1965, only one year after having taken the position. Actually, he resignation was partially prompted by the failure of RCA (of which Newsom was a Director) in its attempt to merge with Prentice-Hall. For the next three years( 1966 to 1969 ), Newsom held the post of vice-president for education at RCA, a position which permitted further work in one of Newsom's special fields of interest, that of educational television.
The brevity of Newsom's tenure at various corporate institutions can be attributed in part to the multiplicity of his interests. As already mentioned, one of his foremost concerns was the educational potential of television, which Newsom glimpsed at the very germination of the new medium in the early 1950's. His ideas were set forth in a landmark text on the subject, A Television Policy for Education ( 1952 ), which held its own for at least two decades as a authoritative source of information on education television policy. Newsom's other interests include religious history(one of his later books, The Roots of Christianity, was deemed "a truly great book" by Normal Vincent Peale), third-world dilemmas (he served as President of American Friends of Ethiopia), and, of course, his starting point, mathematics.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers. This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Provenance
The University Archives acquired the six linear feet of material contained in this collection in April 1991. The documents were sent by Dr. Newsom's son, Walter Newsom, and accepted by Theresa Taylor, at the time acting head of the University Archives.
Photographs.; Reviews (document genre); New York (N.Y.); Articles.; Television in education.; New York University |x Presidents.; College Presidents |x New York University.; Oberlin College |x Faculty.; Correspondence.; Speeches.; Clippings (information artifacts); State University of New York; RCA Corporation; Prentice-Hall, inc.; Newsom, Carroll Vincent, 1904-
- Series I. Addresses.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I consists of addresses given by Dr. Newsom at various functions, meetings, and conferences, many of which correlate with the conference programs found in Series III. These addresses span Newsom's entire early career, but are particularly abundant during his tenure at NYU and during the 1960's in general. The address topics are diverse, but primarily concern pedagogy(including educational television) and mathematics.
  - Addresses, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225818 9
  - Addresses, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Addresses, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Addresses, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Addresses, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Addresses, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Addresses, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Addresses, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Addresses, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Addresses, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Addresses, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Addresses, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Addresses, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225819 7
  - Addresses, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Addresses, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Addresses, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Addresses, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Addresses, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Addresses, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Addresses, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Addresses, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225820 5
  - Addresses, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Addresses, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Addresses, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Addresses, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Addresses, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Addresses, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Addresses, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Addresses-Duplicates, 1951-1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Addresses-Duplicates, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225821 3
  - Addresses-Duplicates, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Addresses-Duplicates, 1960-1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Addresses, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Addresses, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Addresses, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series II. Publications
  Series II consists of two major categories, publications of Newsom and publications about Newsom. The first category comprises articles published by Newsom in various journals and periodicals, spanning the years 1940 to 1973. The second category is a collection of periodicals which either contain articles about Newsom, or mention Newsom in word or image(sometimes finding these references to Newsom requires a minute search). Nonetheless, these latter materials are useful, especially in showcasing the many honors bestowed upon Newsom, such as awards, citations, and honorary degrees. At the end of Series II are publications which relate to Newsom's role on advisory committees at various periods, such as his role as Chairman of the Governor's Committee on New Jersey Higher Education in 1963 (Box 6, Folder 11).
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225822 1
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225823 9
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom-Duplicates, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Publications-Articles by Newsom, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Committee Publications, 1941-1963 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Committee Publications-Duplicates, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225824 7
  - Other Publications, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Other Publications, 1953-1959 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Other Publications, 1960-1986 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - NYU Publications, 1956-1959 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - NYU Publications, 1959-1963 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Other Publications, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Other Publications-Duplicates, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series III. Programs
  Series III consists of programs, which document the various functions at which Newsom gave many of the addresses contained in Series I. Although there is a correlation between the programs and addresses, Newsom did not speak at every function he attended, although he gave a speech at most of the functions covered by the program materials in Section III.
  - Programs, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225825 4
  - Programs, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Programs, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225826 2
  - Programs, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Programs, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225827 0
  - Programs, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Programs, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1974, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Programs-Duplicates, 0 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Series IV. Miscellaneous Materials
  Series IV is made up ofmiscellaneous materials, including the small amount of correspondence contained in this collection, as well as reviews of Newsom's books, and diplomas which he earned. Of especial interest is the seven-page resume of Newsom contained in Box 10, Folder 12, which lists his many positions, awards, honorary degrees, and publications.
  - Correspondence, 1943-1984 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Book Reviews and Promotionals, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Diplomas, 1955-1965 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Resume, ca.1965 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Series V. Newspapers and Newspaper Clippings
  Series V includes newspapers and newspaper clippings which relate to important events in Newsom's career, and provided much of the biographical information contained in this section.
  - Newspapers, 1924, 1955-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225828 8
  - Copies of NYU Alumni News, 1955-1958 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Copies of NYU Alumni News, 1958-1961 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Assorted Newspapers, 1959-1966 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1953-1959 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clipping Booklet, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1969 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1986 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)